welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right
amazing so raven hello
so you are a facilitator at the stoah
for the Socratic speed-dating event we
had two of them so far
and we're planning to have them on
Fridays at 7:00 p.m. Eastern time and
before we press record we were
negotiating or one called negotiate we
were sort of like going back and forth
about you know should we just do a demo
right now on it yeah yeah I feel like we
should do it yeah so I mean there's two
ways we could go about this we could do
it the kind of structure that we've
we've treated as the bottom for the
Socratic speed-dating which is you know
I would choose a question and ask you
and then you each question ask me but we
were discussing yesterday about the
possible variation on this where you
choose the question that you want the
other person to ask you hmm yeah so I
was like well maybe we could play around
with that to today I'm not sure yeah
okay said maybe taken to think about
what question you want me to ask you
okay how are you feeling right now
that's how that's what you want me to
ask you yeah how are you feeling right
now so yeah it's a interesting mix of
emotions there's like those like sort of
like an anger is that I was coming to
this conversation angry not directed at
you
and then there was Association of guilt
I go a shit because I I allowed my anger
to be expressed as I move how's that
gonna land and then the loneliness
associated with that guilt and then
there's like uncertainty if I did the
right thing if that was wisest move even
though there's a part of it that feels
wise me releasing that anger and so it's
like sitting all of this complex
emotions like what to do with it and
then a more fat day comes up online the
stoic principle of accept more love die
fate like all that happened and act as
if you wanted it to happen and then when
I said that sort of like just like
saying that to to you and to another
person to really help just kind of
ground myself and all that hmm Wow
stoicism just like kind of comes to you
when you when you need it let's hope it
continues to even in that act do you
feel like it's kind of metabolizing of
that of that energy and like you can
move forward from that kind of crunchy
place yeah yeah and it was it was good
saying it out loud too cuz I didn't feel
judgment on your end is sort of like you
just accepted that reality and so saying
what I believe to be true in front of
someone and then having them accept it
or just have that essence of accepting
it feels like it accomplished what you
just said great yeah it's actually super
similar but it's a little bit more like
kind of on the meta scale of that which
is when you feel an emotion how often
doesn't involve a physical bodily
sensation in addition to a mental state
mmm
okay so paraphrasing so when you feel an
emotion so what was it like how is it
relate to a mental state or are they
coupled like do you feel both the
physical sensation and also kind of a
mental expression of that emotion yeah
so so even so when you experience an
emotion do you feel a mental state
that's adjacent to the emotion when when
you experience it yeah yeah absolutely I
don't know I've been I've been thinking
about this question and kind of going
back into my own history of experiencing
different kinds of like intense
like deep sense of love or deep sense of
embarrassment or shame or guilt or anger
and recognizing that at those times in
my life
I was really feeling those things and in
parts of my body and the same thing goes
just the kind of micro emotional
landscape that I engage with now like
even today approaching was called okay a
little bit of nervousness here I can
feel it in my in my belly and some of
weird things about the sensations and
why like I think some of these practices
like circling where they really have you
describe the sensations are so important
is because when you sit with them
they're kind of hard hard to describe it
hard to put words to and sometimes it's
not even in like an organ or like a kind
of centralized place it could just be
kind of like a prickling or I don't know
almost feels like a pseudo sensation
like it may not even be a physical thing
that is happening but rather a mapping
of like an emotion onto the body that
kind of creating a feedback loop right
because like there's the story that kind
of emerges alongside an emotion the
thoughts that kind of like ricocheting
images or or whatever it for me like I
have a very imaged base like spatial
mind so a lot of the things that I draw
in terms of associations when I'm
catalyzed by emotion is like flashes of
images and then that kind of circles
back into kind of a on the body
somewhere and those things kind of feed
into each other and create this whole
world that I'm inside of both no not
like a physical level and of immense
level that is the kind of larger
experience of the emotional state s
there's a lot of uh you know K I'm gonna
I'm going to go on gallery reviews to be
compulsory
faces in the recording now and then
there's a lot of good threads to go down
there but I wanted to pause and maybe go
back to the beginning so to speak about
you know how we met
or even before that like
how you got on the stove's radar and the
stuff that you're doing in Portland and
how it kind of relates and then maybe we
can talk about Socratic speed-dating the
project that we're working on so I guess
maybe we start like you know what are
you doing in Portland with your project
and like you know how was your kind of
philosophical intellectual trajectory so
far yeah right now like on the precipice
I'm really excited that I have the space
to explore right now within within my
community in Portland so when I moved
here in June of last year I immediately
sought out a like philosophical
community to engage with for
conversation dialogue and I found this
group called the people's colloquium and
that had been in operation since right
after occupy kind of been the swell of
activity that was happening during that
time a group of people came together and
much like today with this fella actually
they were like you know it's really
important for us to be engaging in deep
conversations about the world and the
zeitgeist and like how we're coming
together as communities and how we're
doing sense making and basically that
object has been nurtured over time and
has grown and has like evolved into this
large like substantially attended like
and really dedicated core group of
people who hold this space for the
community to come and discuss ideas and
I immediately joined in and it's really
made a huge difference in my experience
of moving here just having this
continuous dialogue and this group of
friends to speak about these like large
ideas and share my own ideas with them
the first book that I facilitated was a
book that I just fell in love with it
was the first book of philosophy I ever
fell in love with and it's called hyper
objects by Timothy Martin and I was able
to like kind of explore into the space
of being a facilitator and thinking
about how to make it exciting for people
how to like draw out voices and opinions
in the room
so grounded in a kind of like inquiry so
that we don't end up only scratching the
surface of dialogue and that was my
first foray kind of into facilitating a
book a book of philosophy and then that
just kind of cascaded from there and in
the winter I started doing my own
seminar called the black box women and
we read finite and infinite games and
also like read some pieces like from
Scott Alexander we read meditations
almalik we've had some existential risk
papers by Nick Bostrom
and we're trying to kind of I wanted to
bring game B to this space right and so
the ways that I thought about bridging
from like the philosophical into this
more contemporary space was through
finite of the games because it doesn't
work a philosophy that's attempting to
integrate game theory with Taoism and
other like long-standing philosophical
practices and it really let people up
like it was it was very exciting to
bring that to the group and to see who
really enjoyed with right like people
were like yeah that's like oh my god
this framework is so powerful and it was
also really important I think to can
talk to those ideas and to like bring
them alive in dialog coming into this
crisis right so having kind of that
immediately being in my mind and those
ideas kind of like surfacing and trying
to make sense of things with within them
in the world when approaching this
situation was super powerful as well so
things are really just been leading in
to one another and when we all moved on
to zoom and be the social distancing I
was like honestly I was like this is
great I get to like close the feedback
loop a little bit more in terms of
creating experiences intellectual
experiences that people and engage with
because suddenly the cost of attendance
sounds like lowered dramatically I don't
have to find a place you know people
don't have to negotiate whether or not
they're going to drive there you know so
all of those logistical things that kind
of men
that before I was being very careful and
you know trying to really put in a lot
of work upfront to create an experience
that people wanted I can now really just
begin to experiment in this medium so
those were the things that were on my
mind when I saw the stoah like blossom I
was just like oh my god this is so cool
and initially I was thinking of it like
first of all I wanted to sit in on the
situational assessments I wanted to sit
in on the dialogue I wanted to know what
was happening and I wanted to connect
with community and you know I did the
communit Oz prayer with with you and
Andrew and then saw some of the other
activities that were going on but then
there was a meta level for me which was
like what can I learn from how you are
facilitating this and the different
psycho technologies that you're you're
kind of exploring and so when I sent you
that message on meetup you know the
spirit of which I was like approaching
that conversation with you was just like
there's both the level at which as a as
a participant and someone who is able to
come into the space I feel really really
grateful and then as someone who's
trying to learn how to do these things
myself it's really rich territory for
playing with this psycho technology yeah
what's coming to mind is just the
richness of the online space cuz
personally like I'm enjoying myself so
much more right now doing these events
than doing them in person even though I
had a lot of fun in person and there's
some really rich sweet moments but it's
like all that hassle like administrative
stuff finding a room doing all that and
yeah and the Wellsville came to mind is
like you know Colin Morris from the
existential dance party he's basically
he started his own digital dance studio
now that has the same kind of model of a
stoah where it's based off the gift
economy you know he's sort of its
steward over there he he's kind of like
speaking to people's de mons to come in
and and would Jared Jaynes was it was
mentioning to me it's like sorta like
these digital campfires are just
hang up right there kind of like it's
like proto game B or proto be whatever
gym rat calls right it feels like a good
experiment it feels like the right
experiment to be doing right now oh yeah
definitely and it just it's funny
because it's like the adjacent move this
is something I kind of a model that I
think about a lot which is like what's
the next step that creates a lot of
optionality right and you know
especially for you like you already had
the infrastructure of the podcast and
you already kind of had this network of
full and you've been posting things on
medium and writing and so you kind of
already had this established flow
network of people and we're able to just
kind of like transform it into this this
new form and then like what's really
amazing like for me like the kind of
benefit that I'm getting from from the
fact that you're now opening up and
inviting people to partner with you is
like tremendous right so I get to begin
to play in this space without having
built all of that pre-existing
infrastructure so you're really sharing
as well and then also because you're
coordinating with people it allows for
you to kind of manage the meta scale of
like the stove right and kind of
alleviate the pressure on you to
facilitate everything you were
facilitating you ever be able to it's
just you doing like three events a day
you know what I mean and meeting with
people debriefing and all of that work
allows for you to just steward the stoah
right and that's kind of how you talk
about it and it's very very true and I
can see that that you're stewarding the
stoah and then allowing for other people
who are stepping into their leadership
to create like worlds for people to come
into their own fire astray you know
you're like here's but here's the fire
pit here tend to fire and it's just
really yeah hey that's awesome
feels like you know what's going on more
than I know it's it's got that pretty
good yeah I like that a lot
and so and so to circle back to you
reached out to me and I remember
like I noticed you at the community
invitation like I was saying something
about I think I mentioned it before how
you know I didn't know how to live my
life and there's judgment associated
with that and I thought just dis
evaporated when I realized the insight
where you know no one else knows I live
my life either and I just saw I saw you
just nodding your head just like it
seems like someone pushing the gut like
oh like I just kind of felt you in that
moment I'm feeling people like that into
space - is this like you know I guess
maybe your your senses or our sensors
are upgrading to adapt the zoom platform
I don't know maybe there's some things
going on there and then so like I
already I already had a good feeling
about you and then you meet up and I
just inquired about your philosophical
trajectory you just like look even this
big paragraph over your books long as
for his awesome let's let's connect
write a good feeling and then I I
mentioned to you this idea that I
attempted in Toronto it didn't really
fly and I was calling it philosophical
speed-dating and then I told you the
basic idea about speed-dating mixed with
inquiry and then we were spitballing
back and forth and then the the the term
Socratic speed-dating emerged I think
your friend actually came up with it and
then we came up with a really good
format and then we launched the first
session which was awesome and the second
session was yesterday I think was even
better yeah yeah do you want to like
fill in the gaps a little bit they're
both about that meeting I missed well I
think you've got this the skeleton of
the story in terms of where we kind of
have come together I think like the way
that this is kind of fit into my larger
kind of like narrative or whatever is
that in general I've been really
gravitated towards this idea of inquiry
and in that week that we were contacted
that you contacted me and we were
talking about this I had multiple things
happen that were centered around
questions and the practice of inquiry as
the next step at least for me in terms
of the skill set that I need to develop
least that's what it felt like
all of these synchronicities were
telling me I had already kind of come up
with this idea for for my seminar which
was a question a question based seminar
so we would propose a question
people would come with their like idea
in response to the question and we would
discuss it and so that was something I
was already kind of working on and then
um I'm doing a leadership course with
lamb nation right now the Alwyn
Leadership Academy and that our weekly
modules was about inquiry and then you
came to me with Socratic speed-dating
and there's just like all of these
things centered around this practice of
questioning and I think it it's so
timely so timely because when you're
facing uncertainty and just like the
scale of uncertainty right now is just
it's it's really hard to fathom like you
can really only engage with the
abstraction of uncertainty because like
the time horizon the consequential gap
right that Peter Wang was talking about
and that's even just thinking about
coronavirus right like and we're coming
into the summer time where we know that
there are more climate cataclysms that
are likely to happen all of these other
things that are creating fragility and
that are like pressing on the fragility
of our pre-existing systems or kind of
on the precipice we don't know what's
gonna happen
so returning to the Socratic rites
returning to the question for the
inquiry I think it's just such a
beautiful thing to feel an affinity with
right now and the fact that that could
be a space that we are that we're kind
of bringing was this very very timely
for me and felt very in line with these
other properties of my life right now so
that's kind of my background like the
meaning of this the meaning making of
this work for me as a as a facilitator
yeah I like that it's almost like this
um it goes with the speed dating frame
but it's like an intimacy has to be
developed with act of asking questions
you know like individual intimacy and
then kind of like a collective intimacy
like asking the right questions you know
in this moment and some of the right
questions are about not knowing what the
hell is going on and trying to find out
what's going
and so yeah I really like that and I
like how how you structured the last one
how you're sort of like playing with
different levels and then you kind of
wasn't gonna get three different levels
of types of questions like one that get
to the head heart gut yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah cuz I was I was thinking about
that I'm very intellectual right so when
I am engaging in conversation with
people like one of the things that I
feel the most intimacy is being asking
like a intellectual question like you
know what do you what do you think about
like the search for extraterrestrial
life or what about the biosemiotics like
what it what kind of meaning making can
we create from the from the codes from
genetic code from the fact that we have
these like replicators in our bodies and
we have all of these potential symbols
in our natural environment that can
bring us a sense of beauty and meaning
right so you know for me I was like I
don't want to have a question that gets
at the mind so I was like okay well have
a mind question and I think for this
psychotic dating I had a question about
the future of intelligence so thinking
about kind of AI like how is
intelligence as a property of biological
existence as life existence and our kind
of affinity for creating this
replication of intelligence in machines
in in matter that is non-biological
where is that going to go right so that
was my question for that and then I had
you know a hard question and then I was
thinking about a soul question which for
me a so a question is kind of like
encompasses both things right it's both
what like and even you can even see the
AI question you could turn that to
becomes somewhat of a soul question what
does that mean for the human species
what does that mean for how we make
meaning as sentient beings knowing that
the future may hold this new kind of
sentience so that's kind of like the the
model that I'm working with right now
yeah that's really good I like that a
lot and what came to mind there is that
like you know people who are quite
intellectual and investor like you know
Sam
that they play in that sometimes could
be the best way to get to their heart
exactly connection you know that's
that's that's the entry point mm-hmm
and then I remember you were talking and
then you said you know some of the
spiritual communities don't resonate
with you and I know a lot of people kind
of a critical and circling and stuff
like that because they get bored and
they go here come on let's talk about
something real here yeah people are
sensitive to the spiritual bypass I
think you know and it really depends on
where you are and I think that this is
once again like having a having a more
complex model of people as falling into
kind of different positions but I'm not
you're using Keegan scale or some other
kind of like more amorphous model I
don't I'm not really like wedded to any
model in particular but people at
different places in terms of their
adjacent moves and for some people like
circling is exactly the thing that they
need to create more possibility of
engaging with maybe some of the more
intellectual or technical questions that
we're going to have to face when we're
creating a regenerative future and
everybody's got to know like where are
they coming from and I think the you
know the thing that Jordan Hall talks
about with developing sovereignty like
sovereignty is really the center of all
of this like it's a creation of
communities that are most of sovereign
individuals you know and that is a
challenge for all of us to cultivate
that sovereignty and to have this kind
of like meta awareness of our ways of
being and you have to create all of that
architecture in your mind through
practice right the practice so you know
you just kind of have to like see people
where they are in their own possession
of their own world and not approach it
as if you know what's best for them and
then be the bridge right so they need a
bridge to two people who have moved
through circling and and I think about
this in terms of like post post in the
sense of integrating right integrating
the knowledge and moving on to a new
edge and beginning to engage with new
types of practices right right right
and
with get my guess is that in
intellectual circles you run in there's
more men oh good guess I've been running
way more women yeah you bring the girls
to the yard in this psychotic days
that's exciting for me I like that so
the yeah that was kind of like I wanted
to question about that because obviously
the ratio on the store right now there's
more men than women and same thing could
be just a stoic attractor right and and
I think that's gonna change cuz I'm
inviting you know putting to roil
yourself and I want to have more we
space kinda interest objective kind of
experiences and that was actually one of
the reasons why I came in this this
conversation angry because someone I
think in in a way that I didn't feel was
let's say authentic criticized and
judged the ratio imbalance right now at
the stoah industry kind of like a judgy
way and it even inquired my thoughts
about it or kind of like question about
like what I'm doing to kind of richer
address that or whatever
so imagine that's gonna come up
specially in a kind of intellectual
spaces and for myself as someone as you
know I was philosophy when the
university decoded by ideas very
top-heavy and there's a I know a lot of
men are very intellectual men are very
what I would call disembodied you know
they don't have access of the heart they
just have kind of like their their ideas
in that idea space and I do sense a ego
associated with ideas and this is why I
like engaging a circling these type of
practices because it kind of like a
ground your heart in your mind together
right yes and you seem pretty good in
both those areas so I guess the inquire
there is what is your experience working
if not working with thinking or lack of
feeling with a bunch of men in these
intellectual spaces yeah it's such a no
like I am so curious about this myself
and I'm the agnostic
to the the kind of prescriptions that
people have it in terms of like our
guest hypothesis like people are
presenting a hypothesis about why they
may be and I think that often it goes
kind of unexamined as to what
assumptions they're making about like
what you're saying like what are some
assumptions that are being made about
what you're doing to try and like bring
in people of different genders whatever
kind of increasing the diversity of the
group it's a conundrum for me and I
don't know why I am the way that I am I
don't mind being in a group of men who
are all having a heady conversation I
can take a hang and I enjoy it like to
me that's a that is a domain where I
feel comfortable and I feel excited to
be there
and there's really not much of of
attention for me and I do think that I
bring a different kind of quality you
were talking about the lease pace out of
why I like Rogoff to even start my own
seminar was I had my own intentions in
terms of the kind of kind of space I
wanted to create through philosophical
discourse that was different like I
didn't want to get into these like
argument Eddie's right like this like
sounds like really a superficial level
of argumentation that I found was
happening in some of the more like I
don't know I don't even like all the
male dominated spaces they were male
dominated but like it was a certain kind
of culture that had been cultivated
there where people with with that kind
of disagreeableness would just get stuck
on some point and would be able to we
were missing the spirit of the text they
were missing the spirit of the
conversation and then we would all have
to sit there and the rest of the seminar
all held up by these particular people
who had to have their disagreeable
intellectual conversation I think many
of us have experienced that before and
so I think I had kind of a different
culture that I wanted to cultivate much
more about
creating that weave space and I really
want to get into high-level disagreement
I like disagreement you think
disagreement is extremely important
especially when you're engaging with
ideas because there are competing models
there's a lot of models that share a lot
of underlying structure but they
illuminate different edges and they live
their limited in different kinds of ways
and to get to that edge is difficult
with with a group of people and I think
that that's why I've gravitated so much
towards this conversation of collective
intelligence
I've been following Bonita Roy from the
first time that I was exposed to her
with such excitement because of the work
that she's doing to I think get people
into these edges and even just like
listening to her have conversations with
Jim Wright for example where they don't
they don't agree on many things and yet
they're able to get to the juicy parts
of their disagreement in conversation
and there's so much to be learned from
that because and I don't know like
there's there's the one attractor that's
like we disagree these ideologies are
not compatible and there's no way to
find common ground and then there's like
everything's the same everything is
valid you know everything's subjective
attractor as well and I don't think
either one of those are a very good
option for the kind of uncertainty that
we're tackling right now you know you
have to be ideologically agnostic right
and you have to be seeking where your
where your models are failing and that
requires a kind of disagreeableness you
know a willingness to say hey like
actually I think maybe the model that
you have isn't isn't encompassing this
set of phenomenon this set of
observations isn't explained by this
idea how can we get into that space and
what's maybe another model that we can
use that make sense of these particular
observations and I don't know that kind
of high-level disagreement is is very
hard to cultivate it takes time it takes
like a group of people who are working
on their sovereignty right in order to
open a conversation about let's say like
okay so the
research question is like why do we see
this like demographic asymmetry in the
Shoah why do we see more men than women
that's a question as an open question
and we could create many different
hypotheses to answer that question and
then predictions how would we test those
hypotheses right what would we look for
to figure out if we're on the right
track right and that kind of process
bringing that into the collective space
is certainly a kind of like it's a it's
a dance it's a it's an art form yeah
there's so much richness right there so
if I'll just tell you what what came up
and then we can jam off that so my sense
is this is the the correct order in this
state is to first build good faith the
capacity for good faith relationships
step one and all that kind of the
authentic relating practices you know
gesture towards that then step two is
then speak your truth with with with
passion right but there could even be a
middle step they're worth like having
the capacity to be a performative
agnostic like so you can kind of model
different viewpoints and speak on their
behalf yes yes and then I do think you
need to be able to get flitter between
to like the economic thing but still
speak your truth with some fucking
thumos right and not be shy about it
mhm and what I like about this digital
campfire idea is that it's like that's
really good for step one right let's
gather everyone and keep them warm
around the fire and so they build trust
there and then we were thinking at both
end eyes Jason and Jared were thinking
of having a mediation mediation campfire
sessions we're like the three of us just
riff on like who would be good to have
conversations and then we open up to the
group for the like the remainder forty
minutes so we can kind of source the
collective intelligence of how to like
make it happen they all should be
invited to a database we found through a
letter wiki exchange whatever right
because like you said all these
perspectives are so important to have in
the mix and it can will work you know
like no one's smart enough to be hundred
percent wrong so there's always a little
even like the most radical person
there's some kind of truth there and if
you can invite them around the campfire
make them feel safe and make other
people feel safe around them and then
build a relationship then these juicy
conversations could emerge and have some
follow-up questions but I want to see if
anything came up for you oh yeah I mean
definitely I I think the thing I was
like excited is that there's this um I
don't know and I think that this
actually comes up when when you're
dancing right so there's this embodiment
of all of these different kinds of
qualities and characters and beings and
expressions and it's it's you can become
sumos through dance right so like I can
model I can perform I can kind of put my
extend myself my being into the
expression of acceleration zone for
example I can extend my being into a
game be perspective right I can extend
my being into a model proposed by a
scene to life right so and I think when
we come into conversation we can even do
that with our own ideas we can even do
that with our own ideas which we feel so
personally attached to right and I think
that this is the kind of a move of
decoupling right like that you that
you're being is not the same as the
ideas right like you can create an idea
and have it kind of lift off you and be
something that is allowed to move into
the space and if somebody challenges it
it doesn't come back into you as this
like internalization of harm and that is
it that is a tricky thing right you have
to have the sovereignty in order to not
see yourself attached to the thing that
you're you're birthing it maybe you're
like creating and can have so much
personal attachment boom and I mean for
me it's taken it's taken years it's
taken years in order to develop ability
and once I kind of went over the ridge
line with
and went over the ridge line into the
into the attractor space where if
somebody attacked my idea like in a
seminar I just immediately slumped into
this isn't personal rather than what I
used to slump into which was oh this is
a personal attack and so once I made
that move I was like oh my god Wow now I
can engage in this intellectual space
with so much freedom and so much
willingness to take risks because I
don't feel Interlake this internal
conflict when somebody confronts me
about an idea that I have you know
yeah I'm kind of struck how like how on
the same page we are you know about this
like we we just kind of like met each
other I think like a two weeks ago - yes
like I'm like whoa yeah that's really
really cool and it's like you know how
you you I word it like I stumbled my way
towards this capacity right through all
these kind of like not consciously just
following my haphazardly following my
dame on and then just kind of like
having the ability to do this now like
feed I perform at agnostic and it seems
like you had a similar thing where you
just kind of stumbled your way to it now
with the stoah I want to see if an
ecology of practices can emerge
organically from the collective
intelligence in order to build this
capacity you know like soon for fur for
many people because I think it's it's
needed right now totally honestly I
think that a lot of the kind of
frameworks that you've created are
fostering that kind of thing I mean the
fact that Socratic speed-dating is
centered around questions and also the
fact that as you move through different
phases in the event it goes from a
question that is really open like I
really do like the one to just open up
the the kind of fix the ceremonial
opening is what's the most life or you
that really brings in the person and and
like kind of commits them to the
excitement of engaging with the fire of
others and then as it moves through more
sovereignty is like placed on the
participants right so by at the end
they're generating our own questions
they're leaning into their own curiosity
and developing that practice and also
testing right so you create a quest one
that's essentially kind of like oh okay
I'm trying to create an experience for
this other person where I can connect
and engage with them here's my question
this is my theory about what will work
you got four minutes to test it and you
get to see how did it go immediately and
then the other person and this is what's
amazing about like the the twofold
question like how you can have one
person
in one question and surprise and then
another person asking questions and it's
a surprise you get to see both you get
to test both sides and I think that
that's an amazing kind of feedback loop
that provided by these smaller segments
inside the larger segments of the
Socratic speed-dating in general and
then also the situational assessments
right like the way that your voice comes
forward is through a question and like
the discernment that you use to select
the question also kind of creates a an
awareness for others and you're learning
to write like which questions bring
forth like the most energy and
excitement from the person who is
answering them right so there's all of
this learning around questions
themselves and if people can kind of
bring that to the fore as an element of
reflection that kind of meta awareness
to all of these different events that
you're doing I think that they can even
just begin to learn this through direct
experience which is how I feel like I'm
learning right now I am just literally
learning through direct experience I'm
up with an idea send out there I try and
just let's say that something happens I
integrate the information and then I
come up with a new idea right and I see
you doing the same thing which is like
why I think there's so much synergy
between the two of us now and and then
also saying what Collins do you know
these other folks are doing
we're playing yes yes yeah that's this
well put we're playing which is games
right infinite player is just playing
and creating more options for other
people to join in on the play yes yes
this is really good and it does feel
like play and things are generating from
it it seems like it's benefiting others
I don't know but you I'm not thinking
too much ahead of what's coming forth
I'm just sort of like listening playing
and then seeing what emerges and then
playing with that and it's like they
recursive thing going on
[Music]
and there's something I want to tease
out because there's a proclivity I have
for like sexy coinage and like college I
like kind of like captivating titles
like you know existential dance party
Socratic speed-dating and the lawyers
towards that but I think there's like
there's wisdom and that bias potentially
in a sense that it attracts a lot it's
like its attracts a lot of people right
it's such a tractor that can bring so
many people to play and then there's an
option allottee to filter them out look
right it's like finding the others and
the ones that want to stay can code you
actually sensual dance party this or
that or this right and we were talking
about this yesterday on our debrief
after the event is that this sort of
speedy anything could be repurposed for
so many different kind of I guess like
the levels that you mentioned to make it
sort of intellectual the heart the gut
so maybe maybe yeah like and I'm also
kind of curious if we can workshop
something to how about you give us a
rundown of what last session was like or
maybe the session that's gonna happen
next Friday is going to be like and then
we can talk about the good potential of
this thing mm-hmm
yeah two things one thing that I want to
say in response to your idea of coining
things and making it sexy I think that's
actually really important so that maybe
we could come back to that later
and then second in terms of kind of you
know I'm integrating I'm integrating
feedback and we had a really good brief
for for the next one and I'm also really
looking forward to see if anybody emails
you some some feedback in terms of how
things went
it is kind of strange to be the
facilitator of this event because I'm
alone
I have no idea what's going on in the
breakout rooms what I would I get in
terms of like feedback is smiling faces
coming back to the main session which
did happen and like what I said to you
in a debrief was that on the last one
nobody came back early they waited until
they were forced to come back the main
room and that was a good signal to me
that people were engaged with their
conversation and they were invested in
it to the point where they were running
all the very last minute to kind of like
say what they wanted to say with the
person that they were paired with and I
have to kind of seek those types of
signs right so this is kind of the
challenge of facilitating I think in a
digital space especially with breakout
rooms where if this was a real room I
would be feeling people's energy right I
would be feeling all of the kind of
excitement and elevation and I would be
able to tell if there was one group that
it wasn't really working for I would
maybe be able to kind of intervene in
some way that we create a better
experience for them but the way that
this medium works that isn't really
possible which is also kind of exciting
in a way right because it means that I
have to give up some amount of control
and those people who are in that space
become the facilitators of their own
experience and I have to trust I have to
trust that they're able to provide a
good experience for themselves and for
the other person that they're with right
so I think that I'm learning that kind
of thing kind of just like like taking a
breath and just being like you know what
people are gonna have a fine time
they're gonna have probably a great time
you know and and fine tuning and so like
one of the things that I'll do is I'll
go through the questions that came up in
the chat you know I downloaded the chat
box and kind of see what other people
were bringing up and see if there's kind
of trend in the questions or you know
some some kind of little pieces of
feedback like that and I don't know if
you have any like pieces of feedback
that you feel like you're coming forth
for you right now and yeah I'm still
processing how I'm going to deploy the
next one
I am also kind of thinking about in
terms of the model of the mind on the
heart and the soul kind of thing could
we just like could we compartmentalize
one and like okay have maybe a session
where there's more mind questions and
then maybe a session where they're more
hard questions and then maybe a session
where they're more like the kind of
synthesis of the two you know how can I
like riff how can I be like a jazz
musician of this form right and like
kind of provide full experiments of kind
of focusing on one form or the form that
we print practice at the beginning of
this which is you you know invite the
other person to ask a question that you
want to be asked right yeah so that's
kind of all over the place but that's
where I am right now in terms of she's
elevating my orientation towards the
next one yeah yeah
and what one cheek question that came up
last time I was actually with cavae and
I said what is the question that you
want to be asked if I couldn't know was
asking right and then then that then he
told me then we did it so that that
could be one that we could we could use
and yeah my sense is to develop iterate
until there's like a general one like a
really clear English one it's sort of
like the level one yes and then once
that is like you know robust or anti
fragile or whatever whatever it's gonna
be then others can emerge from it yes
yeah yeah totally
and I'm also you know I'm thinking about
how I can use this and I like some in
our space which is like more
intentionally intellectual right so
we're you know and right now I'm kind of
like scheming as to like what type of
content I'm going to be like kind of
creating or curating for people who are
involved in my seminar and I really like
the idea at this forum and using it as a
way of creating one-on-one conversation
between people and a large group it's a
challenge of zooming I mean like very
hard to have one-on-one interaction in a
large group context it just doesn't
function well and so you have to as a
facilitator create space for that and
intentionally have that be part of the
forum so that other people can have that
experience one-on-one experience with
one another which is super important and
you know especially an intellectual
space like I mean actually I mean in any
on a conversation based space people are
kind of invited to express themselves
when they're in a one-on-one or a small
group discussion that isn't something
that's always available for people when
the large group is the only forum that
is being used and I think that what this
is teaching me is is like how the
breakout rooms can be used to create
kind of cohesion between a group in a
large group and I think that's what
we're doing right so a lot of the faces
that are showing up getting our faces
that I've seen how those situational
assessments or the other events and
provides that kind of space for us to
socialize directly and you know be like
oh hey I saw you I want to ask you this
question what are you like in this way
you know and kind of create that
myelination between these networks of
people right we're like creating more
layers of intimacy there that you know
there's more potential for collaboration
honestly I mean I think that that's the
thing that becomes exciting about this
is that people are investing their time
in this people are
gauging and opening themselves up to
others in this space and we can kind of
lift that Network you know into a
different level of cohesion just through
facilitating these spaces and that's
like the kind of beauty of of just like
facilitating a new general I mean
facilitating is this beautiful thing and
it's very different than teaching right
teaching is like this kind of I have to
smell it and I'm like giving it to you
facilitating is more like I'm just gonna
create this situation yes we'll see what
happens
and then get the feedback and then who
knows what it's like after a month of
doing this like you said this new kind
of opportunity of like emerges because
there's a new need right like there's a
new kind of cohesion that's created
throughout the group that could lift
into a new potential realm of
cooperation and collaboration and
co-creation so but I mean that's not
potential you know yeah it's good to
stay I think right now particularly very
immediate but it's a kind of bet that
you're making you're like and this is
the this is the play of optionality
right you make moves that create
optionality then you're kind of betting
on that you'll have new moves to make in
the future that will bring more
optionality and more potential relations
great and on that do you have like maybe
10 15 more minutes to riff on this I got
the metagame
mastermind it that's six I got to
prepare for that but yeah some so much
good stuff that presented and just
thinking about this whole thing this
project the gift idea too
I'll be I'll be transparent like a lot
of good shits coming out of this thing
right and these type of events that the
model itself and then there's like
noticing just always having to check my
attachment to things so like Collin
starting his own digital dance studio
and then like I'm so happy for him but
then it's like Oh am I gonna lose Collin
right like you know you you've got all
your own sting
am I gonna lose Rayven right so it's
like and then but that but then you know
I check myself my stoicism and whatnot
it's like no that's not that what this
is about this is like a gift right now
and collaboration is king in this space
and it's like that optionality piece
that you were just talking about it's
like what is the proper mindset or
essence or spirit embodiment to continue
to play like that and all these like
cool like things are happening like this
is these I'm just getting this fucking
game on inspired insights and then it's
all my sure one and this could be like
anyone could take ists right like no I
think I was telling this you last night
I cough and I created this for our event
tomorrow on Sunday making friends with
fear and how do you know that and we
could actually use this for the Socratic
speed-dating maybe so a speaker view
ruin what's the view you can see
everyone's face yeah a grid view review
yeah yeah yeah like grid view everyone
has a camera on and so like make eye
contact with someone
mm-hmm in the room and then if there's
something delicious about that because
you don't know who's looking at you they
don't know who's looking at them you
could think oh it is the same person
looking at me right so just that one
exercise alone just creates connection
between everyone and then what we're
gonna do tomorrow we're gonna presents
fear because that's what we want to
build the relationship with this was now
when you're looking at someone just
reflect on the emotion of fear right now
so everyone is feeling the same thing
and feel connected with that that state
and so we can do that with any emotion
really or any kind of state that we want
to prime people with that's a really
good way to just build connection
instantly with a group of strangers and
that technique you know like this
probably is Eagle I want to hold on to
the stole only but no anyone could take
that now you know it's like it's a gift
so it's kind of interesting being in
this space of gifting and kind of
because a gift is doesn't expect
anything in return
mm-hmm yeah I think it's a beautiful
thing to be engaging with and also to
bring boys too
I appreciate that you're like willing to
bring that up as like part of part of
how you're reflecting and
publicly with with this experience
because that's something that we often
feel like inclined to hide right but
like the things that we're sharing we're
worried will be be taken or be lost and
this is the challenge for all of us
right is you know when you think of the
big picture it's like who cares who
cares you know what I mean like people
have been asking Socratic method is so
old right like it's just like who owns
these ideas anyways right and I think
the other thing too is like a like Peter
you know I oh my god a kind the same
situation where I'm like I'm
collaborating this person and I'm like
you know what if they find something
else that they want to do and whatever
but this there's also the bond on the
other side right like we're here
together and like and like we're
creating relationships and there's
mutual benefit a mutual benefit that's
being created and there's also just like
the eye I mean personally I love working
with people I love working on teams I
love the fact that this is an organic
process that we're all coming together
not because we're being paid oh my god
I'm like blown away by this like the
level of coordination that's happening
without any currency moving between us
like usually when when complex kind of
organizations are created they need a
kind of currency in order to maintain
people's a long-term commitment to that
project and in this case you know people
are coming in and out and and sustaining
their relationship with this project
without that like guarantee of a kind of
currency and what isn't what is like
kind of growing or what you've centered
as an alternative to that is the gift
and I think like the the move towards a
way of exchanging from the heart and a
way of exchanging that engenders more
kind of like gifting and like sharing
and also it's teaching us something that
I think is Westerners like we've grown
grown up within the context of a heavily
commodified society it's like oh my god
I can't just go and my
participate without the expectation that
I'm going to be compensated and with
some sort of like currency and still
find value and then also be surprised by
the gifts that others are going to give
me right in exchange for that and it's
like being it's another level of being
willing to play with the uncertainty
right it's like I don't know how much is
gonna come back to me because I've been
aged with this and I'm leaning into that
and that's another level of fear here
right like there's another level of fear
it's like what if I what if I won't get
what I feel like I deserve because of
this I mean the gift really just
completely up ends that way of thinking
about this in general and we need to
practice that I mean I was just done Joe
Burrell
Burres um like seminar this morning and
his whole project is also based like
through the gift and we we need to
practice it and it is challenging and it
does leave us kind of vulnerable but
it's it's a really beautiful way of
creating collaborative spaces and
creating more potential for more gifts
and I'm kind of like feeling into the
art of giving a gift and when I was when
you were talking I was feeling into it I
was getting kind of emotional like it
was like a little bit teary-eyed here
because it's like the scary part is if
you give a gift and no one wants to
receive it like you buy someone a gift
like this is to us I'm at Christmas you
buy a gift you put your heart and soul
into it use at home I'm just I just is
really good and then no one no one likes
it you know the person doesn't like it
and there's the feeling of like
rejection loneliness all that nasty
stuff most not nasty but you know if it
feel nasty
and you have to be like risk that you
know you have to be bold enough to risk
being rejected being unwanted and then
you know being okay with it in a way and
the other thing that came up is like I
did so many free events in Toronto I
didn't like charge anything I didn't
have a gift economy but now that I had
this frame that this is a gift now that
I have this frame that this is a gift
I'm actually happy to have give people
the opportunity to provide a gift if
they're inspired to the stoah because
it's like and this is my I don't know
how they flush will architecture to back
this stuff but this is my intuition is
that in order to give your best gift you
have to be willing to receive gifts in
return you have to feel worthy enough to
receive a gift and that's a whole thing
too if you know if you don't feel worthy
enough to receive a gift and you know
you're gonna corrupt your gift in a way
yeah I put you on mute because yeah yes
yeah and I think once again I think the
idea of sovereignty comes back into this
and I think this may even connect this
would be a hypothesis that I would
propose in terms of thinking about like
why there's so many men in these species
is like this willingness to take risks I
think men in many cases like are just
already kind of set up or kind of like
risk-taking behavior and women have a
tendency to be a little bit more
risk-averse in some cases and so like
there's a develop like part of what
sovereignty I think kind of creates or
pull debates in a person is this like
home a sense of home in oneself so that
you can leave that you can run out the
front door and go and play and go climb
up the tree and like go and and swim in
the lake and do these kinds of
activities that put you at a personal
risk and even though we may not be
putting our bodies at risk by sharing
right yes or by giving a gift there once
again back
the initial question that we started
with emotions have physical experiences
and like the feeling of rejection shows
up as a physical sensation it feels like
something that is that it's like
challenging the your body in a way that
like a risk of falling out of a tree
feels like you know and so cultivating
that sovereignty is is having the home
right for yourself to return to when you
are scared or when you put yourself out
there a little bit too far or when you
kind of like are on your edge in a place
that kind of like sends you into this
fear zone right like I've developed that
method or that Oh for you with your
stomach practice like you're able to be
like okay we are in okay I can return
home okay I remember the way amor fati
shows me the way home to myself and I
can sit with that and process with the
knowledge right like you can actually
gain knowledge from going a little too
far or experiencing a spike in emotional
state and and then your you know your
stoicism or a practice comes to you and
you engage with it and then you return
home and then you're like whoa what just
happened
Wow and then you're able to kind of work
with it and process it and maybe invite
other people to join in within that with
you and that's that's the process right
like that's the thing that we're doing
together and it's it's what we need it's
what we need to do it's it's personal
development that is I think also aligned
with just reaching out and creating
things out in the world it's it's not
just personal development in the
personal development world
it's like personal development that
happens in as kind of like a positive
externality like an externality of doing
other types of work of putting yourself
out there because you're creating art I
mean like I don't know I think of this
like I think a facilitation is my medium
like the people are my medium right that
but like creating structures for
interaction
creating experiences like hosting is my
art form and so I'm expressing my art
and like you said that is like a gift
right like when you express your art
you're like giving your gift to the
world and you really do cherish this
thing and to like be able to kind of
play with that space and return home and
learn from when you you know maybe
create a gift that yeah people might
want to tweak yeah yeah Regas and then
go and be like I inclusion/exclusion but
that being based on someone's own
individual sovereignty right so you
create the space right everyone and
people just decide whether or not that
work so I'd like to end with the thought
that came alive there the first one
you're talking I've I think I arrived
home we wanted to announce that I felt
there not that I didn't feel yeah I
didn't feel quite there when I started
because of what I came in with but I
feel at home you know especially when I
expressed that gift stuff you know that
that's vulnerability there with the gift
I felt really really right to say and so
the when you're talking about this is
your medium right your artistic medium
and I'm viewing these these kind of like
being a really good facilitator is being
an artist of experience oh yeah
and so I want to share an idea that I'm
gonna do hopefully if the person is
willing to do it but even if they're not
a gesture to the spirit of what I'm
aiming at and okay so you know Steven
Jenkinson names familiar but please yes
he's gained my podcast a couple of days
ago he's just Canadian guy he was in the
death trade or he calls it the death
work
that trade or whatever and I was like
some poet and he talks about death his
calls calls it or 'the orphan wisdom and
how the fact that we have a don't have a
relationship with death kind of like
just doesn't give us a culture really
and sort of really really do the full
conversation I had with him and he has
this kind of like elder vibe with and
it's just the flow of consciousness and
he actually talking to him snap me in a
different state of being when I was
conversing with him
and so I was thinking like oh we
wouldn't any Amy unis mentioned at the
end of that conversations that we've
been visited by a god right now and then
you know we have to acknowledge it in a
way and then he kind of tied are kind of
cutting off our truthfulness and then
bullshitting a lying you know
encouraged us to control dominions that
should not be controlled by us and then
this created a deceives in the world
right now that disease is spreading in
more than one way and so that kind of
really heightened this ethical act of
being truthful for me and it almost
feels like I feel pretty vulnerable
being truthful in the last couple weeks
publicly and almost feels it it feels
quite judicially truthful at times but
it's you know it just really felt
ethical thing to do right now ground
yourself in that truthful muscle and may
infuse it with the Dame on to right so
like they have a relationship with each
other so anyway she said we've been
visited by God and I thought well you
know we really cool experience is bring
Steven in and then allow him to talk
around the digital campfire about how
we've been visited by a god and then
collectively we have a moment of silence
to respect the God that has visited us
and then with that I think food is
coming right yeah it's my stomach is
grumbling to so they we've been visited
by the delivery man and uh yeah so we
and there's silence to respect the god
that you know visited us and and then
the youth asked questions to the elder
in this case Steven he's like an old guy
about how to conduct oneself during the
visitation of a God right and he has
this extreme of consciousness thing and
it could be framed basically it's like
someone says your shares of thoughts in
the Q&A but with the delicious framing
of an artistic experience right and it's
kind of like having that that decoration
there and I'm thinking like you know
what like that still could act as a
transformational experience for someone
oh yeah I'm like shit and this liminal
space that we're in the the line between
what is art and what is a spiritual
transformation no longer exists where
it's like an old game a atomistic world
it's like art was like you know boxed
off into this like art gallery that was
called up by rich people so they
neutered art in a way and then didn't
make it dangerous because art is really
dangerous mm-hmm let it be what it wants
to be
yeah the time Turner is running out but
that sounds like a beautiful idea I I've
been feeling the need for something like
that actually is is I mean feeling
called towards a kind of prayer or a
kind of reverence or kind of like
community that where we just like are
holding this sense this God this like I
this idea in mind together has felt like
something from for me just personally as
I've been living in my bedroom basically
for the last three weeks that I would
need I feel like I need I think also
Justin Justin like my own personal level
like I am kind of joyous all the time
now because I am playing in a space that
I find to be so generative and it's like
so beautiful and feeling so many
great like bonding kind of emotions
because I am bonding with people and I'm
collaborating with people and I love
doing that and yet I know about this
crisis and it's in turtle this is
intertwined with the crisis I mean this
is the anti-fertility of humans right
like in them in death we have these
rituals but bring the community together
to make the community strong in the face
of the loss of an individual of an
important individual to the community
and the fact that we have been distanced
from death that we hide death in these
institutions and we push it away and we
make it a kind of professional class
that handles death and in the world that
we live in we have lost our connection
to what life is right you have to dance
with death to find meaning and I'm very
I don't know I'm very excited by the by
this this idea that you're a bringing
forth and this person and can I can get
the elder I also connected to elders who
have practice that their life is like
integration and this dance with death
themselves like I found when I am with
an elder who has integrated that
practice for their life entire life as
an adult sometimes since they were
children there is just this quality of
being around them that is is is like
ineffable ineffable how much they have
to teach and that is like the potential
that we have as human beings imagine if
we grew up in a culture where we were
just intimately engaged with that since
we were children who would be who would
we become as elders what kind of wisdom
would we have that transcends the
immediacy of of whatever particular
embodiment of economics or of governance
settings existing within the framework
of your life like that you could reach
into the experience of someone who is 16
when you're 86 and still bring them
something of value because you you've
really sat with the human condition and
you've really engaged and confronted and
played and integrated for the entirety
of your life and to be invited into that
I think right now is what a lot of this
is is in
being invited into that process to lead
a much more rich life in this in the
stance with with death and the thing I'm
leaving this conversation with is what
you said
is that like you finish so much joy
right now and say that like you know
it's like I was like yeah I'm feeling I
am it's like yeah like I'm feeling joy
all the time but it's associated with
all these like range of emotion like
this rollercoaster of emotions like
anger fear hurt I just when I was
expressing that sadness earlier today I
was it was sadness hugged and joy or
something like that or a sadness when we
enjoy and it's interesting it's not like
guiltiness but just sort of like when I
kind of like remind myself what's
happening in the world right now it's
like it feels such a not a disconnect
but it's like wow this is happening but
I'm feeling this and I didn't feel this
previously so yeah it would like we do
have to go and have to prepare for the
next event I got it any any close your
thoughts before we stop recording well
I'm just I'm you know this has been a
wonderful conversation there's so much
more than we could talk about and I'm
just excited to be collaborating with
you and Phoebe playing with these psycho
technologies and engaging in the space
and I look forward to continuing this
journey yeah nice and so anyone who
listened to this and didn't run away in
fear that you can check out Raven at the
stoah 7:00 p.m. Eastern Time every
Friday and just go to the stow it at CAA
to RSVP for that all right Raven thanks
so much for coming on so much be there